Welcome to the series of videos about functional programming in Kotlin with Arrow. Arrow is a library that is packed with data
types and type classes bringing typed FP to Kotlin. In this video, we're going to learn about the either data
type and what it's used for.
Either is a data typing error that we used to model when a function may return more than one value
Can be either one or the other.
Either is frequently modeled as an algebraic data type in the same way we saw in Option, Either has many cases.
Algebraic data types are modeling Kotlin with sealed classes.
Either has two possible values either a Left or a Right.
In the left side, we usually encode the exceptional case, in the right side we encode the happy path.
This is important because Either is right biased this means that most of the functions like map, filter, and flatMap
will operate over the right case.
We have two main constructors to work with Either.
The Right constructor allows us to bring values into the context of Either placing them on the right.
Whereas, the Left constructor places them on the left.
As we can see here,
we are modeling unknown errors without using exceptions and putting that on the left side
because our computation is mostly going to happen on the end, which is the right side.
Arrow provides a extension syntax for Either. We can easily lift values to the right and left case,
provided the receiver declares a type, in which we know what the other case is.
We can transform the inner contents of Either with several built-in functions such as fold, getOrElse, map, and flatmap.
This might be familiar to you at this time
because we saw the same functions in Option. This is part of Arrow's unified model of programming.
We take all the functional combinators and try to apply them as many data types as possible,
so that all of them share the same API.
We can extract either inner values by using Kotlin's when expressions.
In this case, you can see how the result value will be of type Either
can be easily placed on our one expressions, and then we can branch out logic based on the left and right cases
An easier way to deal with this case, is using fold. Fold allows us to pass two functions. The
first function addresses the left case.
Here we are saying that if we find a KnownError, we should return zero.
The second argument is a function that addresses the right case. Here we have the chance to transform the inner contents of right. A
concretion to the previous fold is getOrElse. In getOrElse,
we're just simply providing the function that addresses the left case. Here we're saying that if it's a KnownError, we should return 0 instead.
Map allows us to transform the values inside an Either.
It operates only on the right case, and that's why we say this Either is right biased.
If we were mapping and there was a left, in that case the transformation is never applied and the left is left untouched.
If we have multiple Either values
and we want to compute sequentially over the right case, we use flatMap. flatMap in the same way as map is right biased.
Instead of dealing with multiple nested flatMaps, an easier solution is to use
errors built in monad comprehensions.
The Either monad allows us to bind over Either results and then bind their results to the right case.
Once we have all of the values unbound, we can then add them up or do whatever transformation we wish in an imperative fashion.
Bind is a suspended function in the Kotlin coroutine system.
When we invoke bind, we delegate the chain call to flatMap. In this way, we can avoid
nested flatMap chains and imperatively compute over the results of Either.
If we bind over a left value the computation will short-circuit yielding the left case.
We can use the applicative builder to compute our different values of Either
That are independent from each other. With the applicative builder we can map or convert into tuples, a set of operations
preserving the type information and preserving their id.
As in with monad comprehensions if we ever find a left value, then we will short-circuit and then return the Left KnownError.
In this video, we learned about Either. In the same way as Option, Either serves a lot of the functions and different
functionality that Option did - fold, map, flatMap.
Arrow proposes a unified programming model for all data types where they all share the functional combinators that are usually expressed in type classes.
We'll learn more about those in the next series. Thanks for watching.