Welcome to the series of videos about functional programming in Kotlin with Arrow
Arrow is a library pack with datatypes
and typeclasses that empower pure functional programming in Kotlin
In this first video we're gonna talk about the `Option` datatype
[Music]
`Option` is a datatype in Arrow that we used to model the absence of a value
In Arrow most datatypes is model as Algebraic Data Types (ADT)
This in Kotlin is represented through seal hierarchies
We can see here, that `Option` can be either `None` or `Some`
If the `Option` has no value
then it's represented as a singleton value `None`
Whereas if the `Option` has a value inside, it's represented with the case `Some`
We can construct optional values
by simply using the `Option` constructor and apply it to the value
In this case the value one (1) is lifted into the optional context
so the resulting type is an `Option` of `Int`
In the same way,
if we want to represent an absent value, we can use just `None`
This is because `None`
it's encoded so that it uses `Nothing`,
a bottom type that can be adapted to any type receiver
`Option` integrates with nullable types from Kotlin
It’s easy to lift a value into the optional context
by simply invoking the ‘fromNullable()’ factory
In the same way,
if we have and already optinal value in it's context,
we can turn into a nullable type
by invoking the method 'orNull()'
In addition to `Option` datatype,
Arrow provides syntax extensions in a different module called
'arrow.syntax.*'
This module allows us to leave values such as
an `Int`, a `String` or anything we want to an `Option`
via `Some` and also to provide `None` values
that match the type that we wanna infer
In addition to lifting other values
and nullable types values to optional context,
`Option` also comes with functions and methods
that helps us compute over that context
One of the facilities we can use when folding over and `Option`
is Kotlin 'when' expressions
We can simply use 'when'
to match an optional
and then contemplate both cases `None` or `Some`
When we fold over an `Option`, we are contemplating both cases
This is similar to the previous pattern matching example,
but in this case we're providing two functions
The first function contemplates the `None` case
in this one we tell what will happen or what value to return
whenever the `Option` is a `None`
In the second case, we contemplate the `Some` case
In this case, we can inspect the value inside the `Option`
and apply any transformation to it that we wish
'getOrElse()' is a specialization of 'fold()'
where we simply state what it will return
if the `Option` was a `None`
We can see this as,
providing just the default value should the `Option` be empty
'map()' allows us to transform the inner value of an `Option`
from one value to another, even change in types
'map()' is only applied in the `Some` case
Whenever we have a `None` case the `Option`,
'map()' just takes no effect and `None` is returned instead
When we have multiple optional values and we want to compute
where the possibility that they will be fulfilled,
we can use 'flatMap()'
'flatMap()' allows us to combine two (2) optional values
and with their result produces a new result
The problem with multiple 'flatMap()' calls,
is that it can become very hard to read
once they're deeply nested
Arrow provides monad comprehensions to deal with this problem
Monad comprehensions like ‘flatMap()’
let us comprehend over the
potential value inside the `Option`,
but they do so in a very imperative style,
where you can have on instruction at a time, in sequence,
stating what is happening
Monad comprehensions are implemented in Arrow at top coroutines
Here the function ‘bind()’
binds in to the left value once ‘flatMap()’ completes
This only happens if the `Option` is a `Some`
In the case that the `Option` is empty
the for comprehension will
short-circuit, returning `None`
In the same way Monad comprehension are to compute sequentially,
whenever we have independent operations that we can compute
in parallel or independently,
we use the applicative builder
The applicative builder has two main features
The first one, it preserves type information,
regardless of the arity of the methods or the number of `Options` we have
In the second one, we had a callback
when all the values are completed and resolved,
only if all the values are a `Some`
In the case that one of the values is a `None`,
the 'map()' never adds and `None` is returned instead
In this video we’ve learn about `Option`
and differents methods and functions we can use to transform it’s values
and to compute over the optional context
In the next series of videos, we’ll learn about more datatypes, typeclasses and
the unified programming model that arrow proposes
Thanks for watching
[Music]