Welcome to the series of videos about functional programming in Kotlin with Arrow. In this video,
we're going to learn about the Try data type. Try is a data type that we use to model
computations that may fail throwing exceptions.
Try is a data type we use to model computations that fail with an exception.
Try is modeled in the same way as Option and Either as an Algebraic Data Type. In the case of Try,
we have two cases - Failure and Success.
If the computation fails with an exception, Try will capture the exception and place it in a Failure.
If the computation completes, Try will place the value resulting from the computation in a Success.
If the computation fails with an exception, Try will capture it and represent it as a Failure.
Try comes with a lot of combinators and methods that allows us to compute and transform the internal values assuming the computation succeeded.
We can use Kotlin's when expressions to contemplate all cases in which a Try may file itself,
whether it's a Failure or a Success.
An easier way to handle the cases of Try is using a fold. In the case of fold, we have two functions.
The first function contemplates
what will happen if the Try was a Failure and had an exception. We can provide an alternative value to return from the fold.
If the Try was a Success, the second function will allow us to transform, or do nothing with it, like in this case.
Recover is a specialization of fold that acts
exclusively in the Failure case. In this case we can see how we can recover from a potential exception provided a default value.
With map we act on the happy path.
If the Try is a Failure, map will take no action, and the failure will be returned instead.
flatMap allows us to combine and compose multiple Try operations in a sequential fashion. In this case,
the results of result1 and result2 are combined to produce a new Try in the form of Success.
Arrow comes with built-in Monard comprehensions that allow us to compute over Try values in an imperative fashion.
Each time bind() is invoked,
it delegates to flatMap and it allows a
Suspension in the coroutine's context to get the value when flatMap will have been completed. If we bind with a Failure,
the computation short-circuits and a Failure is returned instead.
bindingCatch is a specialization of comprehensions for Try and for other monadError capable data types
that automatically captures all exceptions thrown inside it's context. In this case if an exception is thrown,
Try will return a Failure.
In this video, we learned about the Try data type. Try is a data
type that we use to model computations that may fail throwing exceptions. In the next in this series of videos, we're
going to learn about applicative error
monadError, and other facilities Arrow provides to handle exceptions. Thanks for watching.